Cleve Gray
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Alphabetical Files, 1936-2005, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-5, 9; 4.3 linear ft.)
  - Vietnam Protest, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    American Independent Movement
    Angry Arts Committee
    Artists' Mobilization for Survival
    Clergy and Laymen Concerned About Vietnam
  - Vietnam Protest, circa 1969 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    Connecticut Casualties List
  - Vietnam Protest, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    Connecticut Coalition on National Priorities
    Correspondence, Miscellaneous
    Danbury Peace Fellowship
    Individuals Against the Crime of Silence
    Milwaukee Fourteen Defense Fund
    National Committee for a Political Settlement in
    Vietnam/Negotiation Now!
    People's Peace Treaty Spring Action Project
    Selective Service/Draft
    Vietnam Moratorium Committee
    War Resisters International
  - Villon, Jacques and Gaby, 1946-1963, (See also: Schmit, Dorothee, Box 4, F 23) (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Virginia Lynch Gallery, 1986-2003, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Visual Arts and Galleries Association - Waddell, Richard W.,1967-2001 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    Visual Arts and Galleries Association (VAGA)
    Von Hofacker, Marion (re: Hans Richter; See also: Richter, Hans, Box 4, F 6-10)
    Waddell, Richard W.
  - Wadsworth Atheneum, 1973-2003, undated, (See also: Promised Gifts to Museums, box 3, F 59) (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Walmsley, Arthur E. (Bishop, Episcopal Diocese of Connecticut), 1988, (See also: Vestments, Box 4, F 44) (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Warren, CT, 1964-1986, undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
    Public School Plans
    Zoning Commission
  - Washington Art Association (Washington Depot, CT), 1984-1988 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Weber, Nicholas Fox (re: Cleve Gray), 1996-1999, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Weber, Nicholas Fox (edited galley sheets, Cleve Gray, 1998, (oversized material housed in Box 9) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Weiss, Peter - West Cornwall Gallery, 1972-1988, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Weiss, Peter
    Wenninger Graphics Studio
    West Cornwall Gallery
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1974-1997, (See also: Correspondence, Business, Box 1, F 20) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - William Benton Museum of Art - Worcester Art Museum, 1974-2001 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    William Benton Museum of Art
    William J. Jenack Estate Appraisers and Auctioneers
    Wolf, Theodore F.
    Worcester Art Museum (See also: Promised Gifts to Museums, Box 3, F 59)
  - Wykeham Rise, 1968-1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Yager, Karen (re: conservation of Marc Chagall watercolor), 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Yale University, 1968-2002 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Art Gallery
    Divinity School
    Physics Department
    School of Art and Architecture
  - Yau, John, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified (Aggie - Ullu), 1961-1987 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Aggie
    Alex
    Angie
    Anne
    B.
    Barbara
    Bart
    Ben
    Bill
    Bob
    Bobbie
    Buel
    Carol (See: Jerry and Carol, Box 5, F 11)
    David
    Dick
    Don and Michele
    Dolly
    Ellen and Ullu (See also: Ullu, Box 5, F 11)
    Enid
    Ethel
    Florence
    Francis
    Frederic
    Herb
    Irma
    Jean M.
    Jeanne
    Jerry and Carol
    Joan
    John
    Jonathan
    Kay
    Lawrence
    Lee
    Martin
    Michael
    Michele (See: Don and Michele, Box 5, F 11)
    Neil
    Renate
    Tejas
    Thomas
    Tom
    Tracy
    Trevor
    Ullu (See also: Ellen and Ullu, Box 5, F 11)
  - Illegible; Unsigned, 1966-2004, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Oversize Alphabetical Files (Weber, Nicholas Fox), 1998, (See: Box 5, folder 3) (Box 9 (sol))
- Writings, 1936-2000, Series 3:; (Boxes 5-6; 0.85 linear ft.)
  This series consists of manuscripts and drafts, research materials, notes, and miscellaneous writings. Writings by Cleve Gray on a wide range of art-related topics include articles, catalog introductions and reviews. Of particular interest are autobiographical notes in the form of a chronology that Nicholas Fox Weber, Gray's biographer, cited as an "autochronology."
  Among the writings by other authors are pieces about Cleve Gray including the manuscript of Cleve Gray by Nicholas Fox Weber and records concerning three books edited by Gray, David Smith by David Smith: Sculpture and Writings, Hans Richter, and John Marin. Research material survives for the next volume in the series, Naum Gabo, which was never published. Also included are notes relating to Cleve Gray's translation of A l'Iinfinitif by Marcel Duchamp.
  Also found is a small volume of notes and reminiscences about Jackson Pollock by an unidentified author.
  A small number of miscellaneous writings by Gray and others are scattered throughout the alphabetical files (Series 2). Alphabetical files also contain correspondence regarding the publication Cleve Gray by Nicholas Fox Weber and the books on artists edited by Gray. Among the photographs (Series 8) are those used to illustrate David Smith by David Smith: Sculpture and Writings and a few illustrations for John Marin.
  The Writings series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  Subseries 1: By Cleve Gray, 1936-1994
  Subseries 2: By Other Authors, 1952-2000
  - By Cleve Gray, 1936-1994, 3.1:
    Gray's writings inclued manuscripts of published articles, catalog introductions, and reviews, along with artist's statements, his "autochronology," lecture notes and texts, poems, political statements, and student papers.
    Writings by Cleve Gray are categorized by format and arranged alphabetically within each.
    - Articles, Catalog Introductions, Reviews ("Alexander Calder's Circus"-"The Holocaust Triptychs"), 1960s, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
      "Alexander Calder's Circus Drawings"
      "The Architecture of Lionel Feininger"
      Art in America Ceramic Project
      "Aspects of Anonymity"
      "Continuity and Collision-The Baroque Print" (re: Michael Ponce de León
      "David Smith" (includes notes)
      "Duchamp-The Great Spectator"
      "First and Last Visit" (re: David Smith) (See also: "Last Visit," Box 5, F 14)
      "The Gallery, The Museum and The Critic"
      "The Holocaust Triptychs"
    - Articles, Catalog Introductions, Reviews ("Jacques Villon"-"Narcissus in Chaos"), circa 1953-1979, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
      "Jacques Villon"
      "John Marin: The Etched Line" (chapter in Artist's Proof: The Annual of Prints and Printmaking, Volume IX, 1969)
      "John Marin's Calligraphy"
      "John Marin's 1951 Sketchbook"
      "Last Visit" (re: David Smith) (See also: "First and Last Visit," Box 5, F 13)
      "Lee Hall"
      "Miniature Prints: A Traveling Exhibition - The results of the 'First International Print Competition'"
      "Narcissus in Chaos (What's Wrong with the Contemporary American Art World)"
    - Articles, Catalog Introductions, Reviews ("Naum Gabo Talks about Constructivism"), undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Articles, Catalog Introductions, Reviews ("Opening Exhibition at the Cosmopolitan Gallery" - "Thoughts on John Marin"), 1964, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
      "Opening Exhibition at the Cosmopolitan Gallery"
      "Picasso and the Past" (art benefit for the Public Education Association)
      "Picasso at the Ramparts of Tradition"
      "Recollections of Jean Crotti"
      "Remburgers and Hambrandts"
      "Robert Osborne: The Moment of Truth" and "Robert Osborne Comes Home"
      "Thoughts on John Marin"
    - Articles, Catalog Introductions, Reviews (Untitled), 1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
      Untitled, for Art Now: New York Untitled, re: Brooklyn Museum's 15th National Print Exhibition
      Untitled, re: Brooklyn Museum's 15th National Print Exhibition
      Untitled, re: Marcel Duchamp
      Untitled, re: Tatyana Grosman and Universal Limited Art Editions
      Untitled [fragment?] (Reel D314, frame 1706)
      Untitled Fragment
    - Artist's Statements, 1975, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - "Autochronology," circa 1977 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Book Proposal (with Bryan Robertson), undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Lectures and Talks, 1975-1994, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Lists, 1984, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Notes, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Notes, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Poems, 1976-1991, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Political Statements, circa 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Student Papers ("Early Writings," Princeton University), 1936-1939 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - By Other Authors, 1952-2000, 3.2:
    Writings about Gray include a biography, Cleve Gray, by Nicholas Fox Weber, and manuscripts of a poem, student paper, and reviews.
    A significant portion of this subseries is comprised of manuscripts, drafts, notes, and research materials for three books edited by Cleve Gray, David Smith by David Smith: Sculpture and Writings, Hans Richter, and John Marin. Published by Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Inc. between 1968 and 1973, each volume features selected writings by the artist about his work and life, along with photogrphs. Research material survives for the next volume in the series, Naum Gabo, which was never published. Gray discontinued the series when Gabo abruptly changed his mind just as the manuscript was nearly completed. This subseries also contains notes concerning Gray's translation of A L'Infinitif by Marcel Duchamp.
    Also found is "The Resurrection in Art," a lecture by Jane Daggett Dillenberger. Among the items by unknown authors is a small volume containing notes and reminiscences of Jackson Pollock.
    - About Cleve Gray - Cleve Gray by Nicholas Fox Weber (manuscript), 1997, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 28-29)
    - About Cleve Gray - Miscellaneous Writings, 1952, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
      Exhibition Reviews by Mae Anna Quan and Daniel Robbins
      Student Paper by J. Murray
      Poem by Edna A. W. Teall
    - Edited by Cleve Gray - David Smith by David Smith: Sculpture and Writings (Box 5)
      - Manuscript, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - Manuscript and Drafts, circa 1967-1968, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 32-34)
      - Manuscript and Drafts, circa 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - Notes (Archives of American Art microfilm and other sources), circa 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 36)
      - Notes (re: Draft #3), circa 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - "Notes to the Pages" (citing Smith sketchbooks and Archives of American Art microfilm), circa 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 38)
      - Research Materials (notes, transcripts of Smith's writings and copies of documents on Archives of American Art microfilm), circa 1967-1968, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 39-40)
    - Edited by Cleve Gray - Hans Richter (Box 5)
      - Research Materials (interview transcripts), undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 41-42)
      - Research Materials (notes), 1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Edited by Cleve Gray - John Marin, Research Materials (letters, mostly to Stieglitz), 1915-1940, undated, (photocopies) (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Edited by Cleve Gray - Naum Gabo (Box 5)
      - Notes, 1965-1971 (Box 5, Folder 45)
      - Photographs, Lists, Miscellaneous Notes, 1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Edited by Cleve Gray - Naum Gabo - Research Materials (Box 6)
      - "Bijenkorf," 1946-1971, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - "Biography," 1946-1971, (mostly photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - "Chapters - Titles and Mottos," undated, (some photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - "Constructivist Ideology and Constructivist Realism," 1937-1948, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - "Constructivist Philosophy," 1928-1968, (mostly photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - "Criticism," 1934-1968, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - "Early History," 1960-1963, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - "Friends," 1948-1970, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - "Introduction," 1947-1970, (mostly photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - "Miscellaneous Notes and Documents," 1937-1971, undated, (some photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - "Models," 1951-1971, (some photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - "Paintings," 1940-1963, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - "Personal Philosophy," 1946-1969, undated, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - "Pevsner," 1947-1966, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - "Prints," 1959-1970, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - "Science," 1948-1956, undated, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - "Sculpture," 1948-1966, undated, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - "Teaching," 1948-1966, undated, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - "Theories of Art," 1947-1969, undated, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - "Time-Kinetic," circa 1965-1969, (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Translated by Cleve Gray - A l'Iinfinitif by Marcel Duchamp, circa 1966 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Dillenberger, Jane Daggett. "The Resurrection in Art" (lecture), 2000 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Unsigned (Box 6)
      - Notes and Reminiscences about Jackson Pollock, undated, (1 vol.) (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - Untitled Article about Lassiter Spurgeon, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
      - Untitled Poem, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Artwork, circa 1933-1987, Series 4:; (Boxes 6, 9, OV12; 0.45 linear ft.)
  Artwork by Cleve Gray mostly consists of drawings and sketches in pencil, ink, colored markers, pastels, and charcoal; also found are a smallnumber of paintings, prints, and watercolors. Their subjects include figures and European landscapes (many with notes on color), as well as abstract compositions.
  Two works by other artists are an unsigned mobile of paper cut-outs, possibly by Alexander Calder, and a pencil drawing signed Dick (probably Richard Avedon).
  Artwork is arranged into 2 subseries:
  Subseries 1: By Cleve Gray, circa 1933-1987
  Subseries 2: By Other Artists, circa 1970s
  - By Cleve Gray, circa 1933-1987, 4.1:
    - Drawings and Sketches (Box 6)
      - Chalk, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
      - Charcoal, (See: OV 12) (Box 6, Folder 27)
      - Colored Markers, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
      - Colored Markers, undated, (oversized material housed in Box 9) (Box 6, Folder 29)
      - "Illustrations by Gray for Andover and Princeton Publications," circa 1933-1940 (Box 6, Folder 30)
      - Ink, 1945-1969 (Box 6, Folder 31)
      - Ink, 1959, undated, (oversized material housed in Box 9) (Box 6, Folder 32)
      - Ink, undated (Box 6, Folder 33)
      - Ink (Design for Movement in Space, West Elevation, Southern End) 1987, (See: OV 12) (Box 6, Folder 34)
      - Mixed Media, undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
      - Pastels, undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
      - Pastels, undated, (oversized material housed in Box 9) (Box 6, Folder 37)
      - Pastels (portrait of Francine), undated, (See: OV12) (Box 6, Folder 38)
      - Pencil, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
      - Pencil, undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
      - Pencil, undated, (oversized material housed in Box 9) (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Pencil (panoramic landscape near Berchtesgaden), undated, (rolled document, oversized material housed in Box 9) (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Pencil, undated, (See: OV 12) (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Pencil, Colored, undated, (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 44-46)
    - Paintings (self-portrait), undated (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Paintings, undated, (oversized material housed in Box 9) (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Paintings, undated, (See: OV 12) (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Print, 1944, (Reel D314, frame 1782) (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Prints, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Watercolors, circa 1968-1969, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Watercolors, undated, (oversized material housed in Box 9) (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Oversize Artwork by Cleve Gray, Drawings and Sketches, 1959, undated, (See: Box 6, folders 29, 32, 37, 41-42) (Box 9)
    - Oversize Artwork by Cleve Gray, Paintings; Watercolors, (See: Box 6, folders 48, 53) (Box 9)
    - Oversize Artwork by Cleve Gray, Drawings and Sketches; Paintings, 1987, undated, (See: Box 6, folders 27, 32, 35, 38, 43) (Box OV 12)
  - By Other Artists, circa 1970s, Subseries 4.2:
    This subseries consists of two items: an unsigned mobile of paper cut-outs (possibly by by Alexander Calder), and a pencil drawing signed Dick (probably Richard Avedon).
    - Unsigned. Mobile of Paper Cut-Outs, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Dick. Pencil Drawing,circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Oversize Art Work by Other Artists, undated, (See: Box 6, folder 55) (Box 9)
- Audio/Visual Records, 1971-1989, Series 5:; (Box 6; 0.25 linear ft.)
  Audio recordings are in cassette and reel formats. They include a radio broadcast featuring Cleve Gray, several lectures by Gray on John Marin, and another titled "Meaning in the Visual Arts." Other recordings are of Hans Richter and an interview of Jimmy Ernst conducted by Francine du Plessix Gray. Also found is a videocassette, "Glenville School Students at SUNY (Lincoln Center Activity)."
  - Audio Cassettes, 1981-1989, undated (Box 6, Folder 56)
    Cleve Gray Lecture, "Meaning in the Visual Arts"
    Cleve Gray Lecture, Aldrich Museum
    Cleve Gray and Faith Middleton, "Open Air New England," Connecticut Public Broadcasting, Inc.
    Hans Richter [title illegible]
  - "A New Look at John Marin," lecture by Cleve Gray at Honolulu Academy of Arts, 1971, (5" reel) (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Cleve Gray on John Marin, 1972, undated, (2-7" reels) (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Jimmy Ernst interviewed by Francine Gray, undated, (7" reel) (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Jimmy Ernst interviewed by Francine Gray (transcript), undated (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Videocassette, "Glenville School Students at S.U.N.Y. (Lincoln Center Activity)," undated (Box 6, Folder 61)
- Artifacts, 1957-1999, Series 6:; (Box 6, RD 11; 0.45 linear ft.)
  Artifacts include a Chinese scroll representative of those that hung in Cleve Gray's studio, and two of his paintbrushes. Other artifacts are awards - a blue ribbon from the Aberdeen-Angus Breeders' Association, and the Neuberger Museum of Art Lifetime Achievement Award.
  Certificates relating to other awards are filed with Biographical Information (Series 1).
  - Awards (Box 6)
    - Connecticut Aberdeen-Angus Breeders' Assoc., 1957, (blue ribbon) (Box 6)
    - Neuberger Museum of Art Lifetime Achievement Award, 1999, (etched glass on wood base; wrapped package) (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Chinese Scroll, undated, (See: RD 11) (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Paint Brushes, undated, (2 wrapped packages) (Box 6, Folder 65-66)
  - Oversize Artifacts, undated, (See: Box 6, folder 64) (Box RD 11)
- Printed Material, 1933-2005, Series 7:; (Boxes 7-8; 1.25 linear ft.)
  The vast majority of printed material - articles, clippings, exhibition catalogs and announcements, reproductions of art work, etc. - is about or by Cleve Gray. Miscellaneous printed items and publications mentioning Gray consist of annual reports, brochures, calendars, newsletters, programs, etc. Clippings about Vietnam and the Vietnam protest memorabilia reflect Gray's passionate involvement in the anti-war movement, and include a small number of items that were written by or mention him.
  Additional printed material is scattered throughout the alphabetical files (Series 2).
  - Articles (Box 7)
    - About or Mentioning Cleve Gray, 1949-1999, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Art Topics, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - By Cleve Gray, 1948-1989 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Book Chapter by Cleve Gray, "John Marin: The Etched Line" in Artist's Proof: The Annual of Prints and Printmaking, Volume IX, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Book Review by Cleve Gray, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Clippings (Box 7)
    - About or Mentioning Cleve Gray, 1947-2005, undated, (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 7-12)
    - Art-related, 1971-1999 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Vietnam Protests, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements (Box 7)
    - Cleve Gray Solo Exhibitions, 1946-2004, undated, (7 folders) (Box 7, Folder 15-21)
    - Cleve Gray Group Shows, 1947-2003, undated, (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 22-27)
    - Cleve Gray, Juror, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Other Artists' Exhibitions, 1968-1980 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition Reviews by Cleve Gray, 1961-1966 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Invitations to Events Honoring Cleve Gray, 1968-1999 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Lecture Announcements, Cleve Gray, Speaker, 1986, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Letters to the Editor by Cleve Gray, 1960-1968 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "Miscellaneous Printed Items," 1963-1965, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Poem by Cleve Gray, "My Insomnia," 1976 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Postcards of Prague (blank), undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Publications Mentioning Cleve Gray, 1963-2005, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - Reproductions of Art Work (Box 8)
    - By Cleve Gray, circa 1933-1952, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - By Cleve Gray, 2001, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - By Other Artists, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Vietnam Protest Ephemera, 1968-1969, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Wine Label, West Coast Chardonnay, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Photographs, circa 1934-2002, Series 8:; (Boxes 8-10; 1.15 linear ft.)
  Photographs are of artwork, events, people, places, and miscellaneous subjects. Also found with this series are photographs used to illustrate David Smith by David Smith: Sculpture and Writings, and a small number of negatives and color transparencies.
  Most of the artwork appearing in the photographs is by Cleve Gray and consists of drawings, paintings, and sculpture arranged by medium. Among them are destroyed paintings, and an original print of Photo Abstraction by Gray, circa 1934. Of particular note are photographs of preparatory drawings for Threnody, the work in progress, and completed panels. Other artists represented are: Louise N. Grace, Jacques Lipchitz, John Marin, Hans Richter, and Jacques Villon.
  Photographs of people are mainly portraits of Gray, and views of him with Francine and their family. Among these are one of the family with their infant son, Thaddeus, by Irving Penn; a portrait of Gray at about age three (a modern copy print); and other portraits of him by Cornelia Lavin, Alexander Liberman, Frances McLaughlin-Gill, and Nancy Tutko. Other individuals pictured are Hans Richter and some of his descendants. Photographs of places consist of Gray's studio.
  Events are an unidentified exhibition opening and miscellaneous subjects are exhibition installations.
  A small number of photographs are scattered throughout the alphabetical files (Series 2).
  - Artwork by Cleve Gray (Box 8)
    - Paintings, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Paintings (Across - Mystery, Mystery), undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Paintings (Night, Ochos Rios - Tea at Puteaux), undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Paintings (Todtentanz #2 - Young Boy with a Cutlass, and unknown titles), undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Paintings, Destroyed, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Photograph, Photo Abstraction (copy print), undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Photograph, Photo Abstraction (original photograph), circa 1934, (oversized material housed in Box 9) (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Sculpture, 1962, undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Threnody, Preparatory Drawings, circa 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Threnody, In Progress, circa 1972-1973, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 23-24)
    - Threnody, Panels, circa 1974 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Artwork by Other Artists, undated (Box 8, Folder 26)
    Grace, Louise N. Grace
    Marin, John
    Lipchitz, Jacques
    Richter, Hans
    Villon, Jacques
  - Events, Exhibition Opening (unidentified), undated, (oversized material housed in Box 9) (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Illustrations (Box 8)
    - David Smith by David Smith: Sculpture and Writings, edited by Cleve Gray, undated, (See: Box 10) (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - John Marin, edited by Cleve Gray, undated (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - People, Cleve Gray (Box 8)